Of today's דף daf, *daf* is דף daf, מה *daf Mem He*
45 and we pick up at the bottom of מד עמוד ב
*Mem Dalet amud bet* and we're dealing with the issue about somebody
that goes חוץ לתחום chutz l'techum. *chutz l'tchum*. The first משנה mishna
*mishna* spoke about going חוץ לתחום chutz l'techum *chutz l'tchum* because of
an אונס *ones*, you were forced outside of the תחום techum *tchum*.
In this משנה mishna *mishna* talks about going out because of a
מצוה mitzvah *mitzva*, it doesn't speak or with רשות reshus *reshut*. מי
שיצא ברשות *Mi sheyatza b'reshut*, it doesn't amplify what that is. We'll
see about that in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. And there it says
you actually have 2,000 אמות amos *amot*. So the question now that's
being debated in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* between רבה *Rabba* and רב
Rav שימי בר חייא *Rav Shimi bar Chiya* is what happens
if case of the משנה mishna *mishna* you went out, you found
out that you no longer needed, your services are no longer needed,
you have 2,000 אמות amos, *amot* from where you are.
How does that relate to your original place where you started? And
the debate is if you stepped outside your original 2,000 אמות amos,
*amot* from your home. Here's your home and here's you and you
went there and you this piece of paper is like you know
whatever this is like your original תחום techum *tchum* okay and you
went over here. So is it now you have 2,000 אמות amos
*amot*? So does that 2,000 אמות amos *amot* get you back to
your house, right, or no? Or it's just you have this, it
doesn't combine with your previous
תחום techum *tchum*. So the first position was that if you're within
the 2,000 אמות amos *amot*, so then you really can already get
back to your house, then you revert back to your old תחום
techum. *tchum*. But if you leave the 2,000 אמות amos, *amot*, then
you just have your new תחום techum *tchum*. That was the first
position. The other position says no, even if you leave the 2,000
אמות amos, *amot*, because they overlap, okay, that allows you to go
back to your house. And according to one version in רש״י Rashi,
*Rashi*, not only does it allow you to go back to your
house because they overlap, it gives you actually both תחומין techumin. *tchumin*.
So you can go back to your house and get all the
way back here and you can get from your new place all
the way forward. You actually have the combination of the two תחומין
techumin *tchumin*. So that is the question. Once you leave the original
2,000 אמות amos, *amot*, do you get are you able to have
the overlap allow you to get back even to get back to
your house and maybe even give you both. Okay. And that's so
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* picks up now the last line of מד
עמוד ב *Mem Dalet amud bet* with that discussion. והיכא דלא שבק
ביה לא *V'heicha d'lo shavak bei lo*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says if you actually started שבת Shabbos
*Shabbat* within a walled space, it had been talking about a cave,
then obviously that would be different because then that would mean that
the entire space even if it was being enlarged would be like
one space. But are you trying to tell me without that special
case you would not say this idea of overlap? והתנן *V'ha tnan*,
top of מה עמוד א *Mem He amud aleph*, we taught in
the משנה mishna *mishna*, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר *Rabbi Eliezer omer*,
שתים יכנס שלוש לא יכנס *Shtayim yikanes shalosh lo yikanes*.
So if he steps, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* says your
four אמות amos. *amot* are two אמות amos *amot* in each direction.
And if somebody steps over the 2,000 אמה ama *amah* line in
a normal case, within two אמות amos *amot* of the 2,000 אמה
amah. *amah* line if he stepped over, he can go back. Okay
why? Because his two אמות amos. *amot* which he has now that
he overstepped will overlap with the 2,000 אמות amos. *amot* and that'll
allow him to come back. More than that, three אמות amos, *amot*,
he's already completely outside, even his two אמות amos *amot* won't get
an overlap and he cannot enter back. So מאי לאו *mai lav*,
isn't the explanation here רבי אליעזר לטעמיה *Rabbi Eliezer l'teimei*, רבי אליעזר
*Rabbi Eliezer* is going according to his reasoning, דאמר והוא באמצען *d'amar
v'hu b'emtza'an*, the four אמות amos. *amot* he's in the middle of
them so there's two אמות amos, *amot* in each direction. וארבע אמות
amot. דיהבו ליה רבנן rabbinic *V'arba amot dyahavu leh Rabbanan*, and those
four אמות amot, *amot* the רבנן rabbis *Rabbanan* gave, כמאן דמבלעו דמו
*k'man d'mivlu damu*, are like they are absorbed or I'll say overlap
with the 2,000 אמות amot. *amot* וקא מעייל *v'ka me'ayel* and you
can enter in to your 2,000 אמות amot *amot* and go all
the way back home.
So you see that if you have a new תחום tchum. *tchum*
and it overlaps with your old, you're allowed to go back into
your old. Okay and certainly you can get back home and you
can have your old תחום tchum *tchum*. And maybe as we're saying
maybe you have both but certainly you also have your old one.
So you see אלמא הבלעת תחומין techumim מילתא היא *alma havalat tchumin
milta hi*. You see absorption or again overlap of the תחומין tchumin
*tchumin* is significant and allows you to restore minimally restore your old
תחום tchum *tchum*. אמר ליה Amar leih רבה בר בר חנה לאביי
*Amar leh Rabba bar bar Chana l'Abaye*, so רבה בר בר חנה
*Rabba bar bar Chana* said back to אביי Abaye *Abaye*, מי דרבי
אליעזר קמותבת ליה למר *mi d'Rabbi Eliezer k'mosift leh l'mar*? Your challenging
the master meaning it was רבה *Rabba* I believe, רבה *Rabba* you're
challenging רבה *Rabba* from רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*? So maybe the rabbis
disagree exactly for that reason. Maybe the rabbis say when you step
over the 2,000 you can't go back because that's exactly what they
debate, that they actually are saying that they don't allow the overlap
to be significant. So maybe that's exactly the debate and maybe we
rule like the חכמים Chachamim *chachamim* and the overlap doesn't get you
anywhere. אמר ליה amar lei, *Amar leh*, he said back to him,
אין *in*, yes I'm going to bring my proof from רבי אליעזר
*Rabbi Eliezer* דשמיע לי מיניה דמר *deshmiya li minei d'mar* because I
heard from the master from the same רבה *Rabba* I heard from
him, עד כאן לא פליגי רבנן rabbinic. עליה דרבי אליעזר אלא לדבר
רשות *ad kan lo pligi רבנן Rabbanan. alei d'Rabbi Eliezer ela l'dvar
reshut*. When do they argue that the overlap doesn't help you? That's
only when you overstep, you went outside of the תחום tchum. *tchum*
for a discretionary matter, meaning that you really weren't supposed to step
outside. That's funny because our משנה mishna's speaks about המי שיצא ברשות,
hami sheyatza bireshus, but here רשות here meant that it was your
choice and there was not a מצוה mitzvah and therefore they say
the overlap doesn't help you. אבל לדבר מצוה, aval l'dvar mitzvah, if
you stepped outside the תחום tchum for a מצוה mitzvah purpose, like
in our משנה Mishna which is why you have 2,000 אמות amot
when you leave, not 4, not 4 אמות, amot then מודו ליה
modu lei they would agree. So his tradition was was that this
debate of when you step outside the תחום tchum, normally, and you
have 4 אמות, amot. can that 4 אמות amot, get you back
into the תחום tchum. or not when you go beyond the 2,000
because of the overlap, he said that's not a a principal debate
of whether the overlap works. That's a question of whether we're going
to let it work in this case because you shouldn't have gone
חוץ לתחום. chutz l'techum But in our משנה Mishna when you're allowed
to go חוץ לתחום chutz l'techum and you actually have 2,000 אמות
amot. when you leave, okay, if that overlap, if that creates an
overlap, then everybody would agree that you'd be allowed to go back
home and according to one version of רש"י, Rashi, not just go
back home, you might even be allowed to have both תחומין. So
to go maybe even up to 8,000 אמות amot because both points
you would be would be your acceptable תחום. tchum. Yes.
We haven't done it yet, but at some point we're going to
actually define in an unwalled city, what is the city limit?
Yes. That is coming up. Okay. Now, I should say before we
go on, I do want to mention one thing because I did
a little checking yesterday. First of all, we mentioned in yesterday's דף,
right, that the whole question, this is the important issue about do
we rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel by דיר וסהר dir u'sohar
where somebody goes outside the תחום techum and then they find themselves
in a walled space and the very relevant example I gave was
your plane landed on שבת Shabbos and now you're you know you
can totally step off the plane and into be straight into the
airport or into that what do you call that thing again? Jetway.
So totally in a walled space. Do we rule like- so first
of all there's an issue of יש תחומין למעלה מעשרה. yesh techumin
l'malah me'asarah. But also there's an issue about do we rule like
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that said that even if you didn't start
in the walled space, you're allowed the entire walled space. And so
yesterday's דף, right, if you'll remember at one stage the גמרא Gemara
says when it speaks about making the wall about people, it says
how of course the wall would work because רב Rav? says we
rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and that a wall works. So
why do we assume we're going like רב? Rav So anyway, that's
one of the proofs that ראשונים Rishonim bring that because the גמרא
Gemara takes it for granted that position of רב rav. that we
rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that that is the הלכה halacha
that even if you enter into a walled space, if you're in
a walled space after you went out חוץ לתחום chutz l'tchum, that
you actually are given the entire walled space. Now, I do also
want to mention two other just as important points before we move
on about that. One is the issue if you remember when speaking
about walled space, the משנה Mishna also mentioned at the beginning of
the פרק, perek, it says הוליכוהו לעיר אחרת נתנוהו בדיר וסהר.
holichuhu l'ir acheres nesanuhu
b'dir u'sohar.
So if after you're leaving your 2,000 אמות, amot, this is talking
about that you were forcibly removed, you were placed into a barn,
that's דיר וסהר, dir u'sohar, but the first thing says or to
another
city. So what's the case of the other city? So this is
an important debate of the ראשונים. Rishonim. A number of ראשונים Rishonim
and the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch rule that that only means a
walled city, so it's just another example of being placed in a
walled enclosure. But the רמב"ם Rambam and other ראשונים Rishonim rule and
some even are willing to rely on this בשעת הדחק bishas hadchak
that it means even in an unwalled city. Because the same way
when I start שבת Shabbos in a city, I have the entire
city doesn't count against my 2,000 אמות, amot counts as one space,
if I was taken out חוץ לתחום chutz l'tchum and deposited in
a city, even an unwalled city, according to some ראשונים, Rishonim, I
can go the entire city. So that has a huge implication because
now the whole issue about like landing in an airport and we
said what if you have to walk on the tarmac, getting off
of a boat and so on, no longer is it an issue
about being in a walled enclosure, as long as you were brought
into a city and it was forcibly you were on the plane,
you didn't mean to you know the plane got delayed, you didn't
control it or whatever, so that actually would have the same הלכה.
halacha. The airport's part of the city? The airport- well I mean
you look at a map and whatever, but if for תחומין purposes
it's part of the city, right, a lot of right. Anyway, so
that's very important those two things because that does come up particularly
with like delayed planes and boats and other types of issues, those
two cases. And the last thing I'll just mention is the issue
that Michael kept on asking, he said this idea that you can
go the entire space, you know, if you're in a walled enclosure,
the משנה Mishna says when you were forcibly extracted and put in.
And he said well what if you willfully do that? So my
response was no no no, the משנה's mishna emphasis of forcibly is
to- because of a case that when you were then forcibly brought
back, you go back to square one, but not for the issue
about being put in an enclosure. Actually it's a מחלוקת ראשונים machlokes
Rishonim that question. And so some- so if you willfully leave and
then find yourself which again doesn't mean that you chose to get
on the flight and then the flight got delayed, it means that
you actually planned, you know, to fly over שבת Shabbos, and land
or whatever, if you willfully did it, then it's a מחלוקת ראשונים
machlokes Rishonim whether you can walk in the entire- Enclosed space. So
that's an actual debate exactly about that point. So that's just a
little practical הלכה, halacha, again, this really comes up in the questions
about delayed flights. Okay, let's now continue in the גמרא. Gemara Now
we're talking about leaving כדבר רשות kidvar reshus where you actually have
a מצוה mitzvah. and you have a new 2,000 אמות, amot and
if it overlaps then according to the emphasis, you know, the upshot
of the previous discussion, you would get to actually go back to
your original city. And now וכל היוצאים להציל חוזרים למקומן. vechol hayotzim
lehatzil chozrin limkoman. Now at the end of the משנה mishna says,
and anybody who goes out to save, save you know, can go
back to their original place. So the גמרא Gemara is bothered because
originally the משנה mishna sounds like you just have 2,000 אמות. amot.
This seems like a blanket allowance to go home. Which one is
it? 2,000 אמות amot. or a blanket allowance to go home? So
the גמרא Gemara says, ואפילו טובא, va'afilu tuva, even even a lot?
והאמרת רישא אלפיים אמה ותו לא? veha'amarta reisha alpayim ama vesulo? That
when you go out you have a new 2,000 אמות amot and
if you wind up, by the way I should say, in a
new city, you went out
to help someone give birth or something like that, then you're like
a new city, so you have the whole city and 2,000 אמות.
amot אטפיי, atfayei, but you have your new space. It's not that
you can go back regardless. So ותו לא vesulo and not more,
so how come the end of the משנה mishnah says you can
always go back? So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav שחוזרים בכלי זיין למקומן. shechozrin bichlei zayim limkoman. It's not
meaning to say to challenge the idea of 2,000 אמות. amot What
it's coming to do is tell you even a bigger קולא kula
in a different area. That if you went out להציל, lehatzil, להציל
lehatzil is to save someone, and save here has particularly the connotation
of save from being attacked by the enemy. So you went out
with your, you know, with your weapons. Now you can actually go
back with your weapons even though you'll be carrying. You can go
2,000 אמות, amot. we're not extending necessarily, although I'll get back to
that in a minute, we're not necessarily extending the amount you can
travel, but what we're saying is you can even carry your weapons
back with you and it's מתיר matir in carrying. Why is it
מתיר? matir? Yes, I know it's a good question. So I will
tell you, let me just say, the reason it's מתיר matir in
carrying, this is not a היתר סופו משום תחילתו, heter sofo mishum
techilasah, it's specifically as we're going to see is because if you
were fighting the enemy, even if you think you've won the battle,
as soon as you deposit your weapons you're obviously exposing yourself. So
you can remain armed even at the, you know, even at the
end to continue to protect yourself until you get home. So that's
the emphasis. So Michael says, why does it say למקומן? limkoman? So
actually, although the גמרא gemara is unclear about this, you know, להלכה
l'halacha we rule that in this case, yes, because of the issue
that you're fighting the enemy you can go all the way home.
The 2,000 אמות amot. is when you leave for other reasons. When
you leave to fight the enemy, then no matter how far you
went, you're allowed to go home and you're allowed to carry your
weapons with you. Although the גמרא gemara didn't emphasize that point. Yes,
because it's פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. Okay, so carrying weapons home is
not פיקוח נפש? pikuach nefesh?
Yes, well that's what we're going to see, it is. Because then
as soon as you deposit your weapons, I'm, you know, the enemy
is still out there even if they ran away, as soon as
you deposit your weapons you're inviting a new attack. So let's read
the גמרא Gemara a little bit and then I'll take the questions,
okay? ומאי קשיא? umai kushya? Now the גמרא Gemara, said, why was
this whole thing a problem anyway? You said, oh the end of
the משנה mishnah says you can go back regardless and the beginning
said 2,000 אמות. amot? דילמא להציל שאני. dilma lehatzil shani. Maybe
meaning I didn't even understand the question to begin with. It's obvious
what the difference is. When you're going out for other reasons you
have 2,000 אמות, amot when you're going out to like defend against
attack, then you can always go back. So there wasn't even a
problem, להציל lehatzil was you know that was what made it clearly
different. אלא הא קשיא הא קשיא. ela hei kashya ha kashya. So
this is really what led to the problem which then led to
the answer about carrying your weapons. דתנן, detnan, we have a משנה
mishnah and this is a משנה mishnah in ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
which is quite interesting. That's where it spells out why you can
go חוץ לתחום, chutz l'tchum. not here in עירובין. Eruvin. And here's
what the משנה mishnah says. בראשונה לא היו זזים משם כל היום
כולו. berishonah lo hayu zuzim misham kol hayom kulo. Originally when the
עדים eidim came, the witnesses came to testify on the new moon
and they came on שבת, Shabbos so once they got to where
they needed to get to, they couldn't leave the courtyard, they couldn't
leave where they were because you know they went חוץ לתחום chutz
latchum, and they had not yet established a special exception of somebody
who left for דבר מצוה. devar mitzvah. So התקין hikin רבן גמליאל
הזקן, Rabban Gamliel haZaken, so רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel the elder established
a תקנה, takana, שיש להם אלפיים אמה לכל רוח. sheyesh lahem alpayim
ama l'chol ruach. That these witnesses have 2,000 אמה amah because they
went for a licit purpose to testify about the new moon. ולא
אלו בלבד אמרו, velo elu bilvad amru, and when they did this
they did not just say about these people, אלא אפילו חכמה הבאה
לילד, ela afilu chachama haba'ah leyled,
even a midwife who's coming to help a woman give birth, והבא
להציל מן הגיס ומן הנהר ומן המפולת, veha'ba lehatzil min hagayis umin
hanahar umin hamapolet, somebody who's coming to save people from an attacking
army or from a river that's you know that's flooding or from
a building that's collapsing ומן הדליקה umin hadleika or a fire, so
you're like the volunteer fire brigade, הרי הן כאנשי העיר, harei hein
k'anshei ha'ir, you become, if you've entered into a new city as
a result, you become like the people of the city ויש להם
אלפיים אמה לכל רוח veyesh lahem alpayim ama l'chol ruach and 2,000
as by the way about this 2,000 is that if you've entered
into a new city, then you get the whole city plus 2,000,
not just 2,000. Okay, so now the, okay, so now we have
a problem though because here it clearly includes the case of להציל...
lehatzil... to save somebody from armies, right, from an attack, and it
says 2,000 אמות. amot And our משנה mishna says if you went
out להציל lehatzil you can go all the way back home. So
which is it? Okay, so you can't just say להציל lehatzil is
different, because we have one case of להציל lehatzil that's 2,000, and
our משנה mishna. להציל lehatzil that says you can go back. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אלפיים אמה לכל רוח ותו לא? alpaim amah
lechol ruach vetu lo? What, just 2,000 and not more? ואמרת כל
היוצאין להציל חוזרין למקומם, veamarta kol hayotzin lehatzil chozrin limkomam, אפילו טובא?
afilu tuva? The משנה mishna says you can go back home even
a lot. So, you know, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav, שחוזרין בכלי זיין למקומם. shechozrin bichlei zayin limkomam. No,
that means carrying their weapons. So according to this approach, actually it
would be an interesting mix. Yes, you're limited to 2,000 אמות, amot,
but you're allowed to actually violate, not violate, but you're allowed to
carry your weapons because of פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. This obviously would
be assuming that you don't need to go all the way back
home for פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh purposes. Okay, so the idea of
travel, that'll be limited to 2,000 אמות. amot The idea when our
משנה mishna says you can go back, it's really funny because it's
not really talking about the idea of how of going and תחומים,
tchumim, it's really talking about the idea of carrying and you can
carry your weapons. Okay, and now the גמרא's Gemara going to elaborate
on this, כדתניא, kedatanya, like we taught in the ברייתא. braita. בראשונה
היו מניחין כלי זיינם בבית הסמוך לחומה. barishonah hayu manichin klei zaynam
beveit hasamuch lachomah. They used to leave their weapons in the house
near the city wall after they fought off the attack. פעם אחת
הכירו בהן אויבים. paam achat hikiru vahen oyvim. So one time the
enemies recognized that they had deposited their weapons, even presumably after the
battle. It's quite interesting, by the way, I must say, to imagine
what the historical circumstances of all of this is. Like a group
of Jewish, you know, soldiers fighting off non-Jews in the times the
משנה's mishna, being written. Like what are we talking about? Are we
talking about חשמונאים Chashmonaim times? That's the only time I could imagine
that this is a relevant, that this would be actual practice. Okay.
What? The Roman invasion? Yeah, what,
you mean when they laid siege to ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Yeah, did you
actually have,
or the בר כוכבא Bar Kochba revolt?
Maybe the בר כוכבא Bar Kochba revolt. Maybe the בר כוכבא Bar
Kochba revolt. I don't know, because most of the time they were
fighting like a guerrilla warfare, right? So it wasn't like a troop
that was running after or something. You'd have to decide, it's fascinating
to try to guess when what the circumstances were. Okay, anyway, הכירו
בהם אויבים, hikiru bahem oyvim, so the enemies recognized that they were,
they were unarmed, ורצו אחריהם, veratzu achareihem, and they chased after them,
ונכנסו ליטול כלי זיין, venichnesu litol klei zayin,
so they went back to this, to this house, to this armory
to get their weapons, ונכנסו אויבים אחריהם, venichnesu oyvim achareihem, and the
enemy was chasing after them. דחקו זה את זה, dachaku zeh et
zeh, so the Jews who were getting to get, who were going
to get their weapons started, you know, pushing one another to get
to their weapons, והרגו זה את זה יותר ממה שהרגו אויבים, vehar'gu
zeh et zeh yoter mimah shehar'gu oyvim, and they killed one another
in the sort of fight to get their weapons more than what
the enemies killed, the enemies killed them. You know, this is, by
the way, a trope which is quite interesting, which maybe is meant
as like a מוסר, mussar, that it happens a number of times,
right? You remember that, the shoes with the nails, that they thought
the enemy was there and then they were all pushing to get
out and they wound up, you know, killing one another. And you
have the case about the fighting for the לולבים, lulavim, remember that?
You know that story about how they used to leave their לולבים
lulavim and they would fight for the לולבים? lulavim? Things to be
like a מוסר mussar here about how the in-fighting, you know, we
do ourselves more harm, we're our own worst enemy, more than what
the enemy does to us. What? Spiritual?
Right. So anyway, okay, so therefore באותה שעה התקינו, beotah shaah hitkinu,
at that moment they established שחוזרין למקומן בכלי זיין, shechozrin limkoman bichlei
zayin, they can actually keep their weapons on until they got back
safely and securely home. Okay, so according to this, the 2,000 אמות
amot. limit might apply, assuming it's not a פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh
concern, but you can continue to be armed until you get home.
רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar. Yeah, let
me, I want to read a few more answers. רב נחמן בר
יצחק אמר, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar, and רב נחמן בר יצחק
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak says, no, there's another difference about whether you
have only 2,000 אמות amot to go home. Put aside the issue
of being armed or not. How far can you travel? Is it
2,000 אמות amot or home? So there's a difference. לא קשיא. lo
kashya. כאן שנצחו ישראל את אומות העולם, kan shenitzchu Yisrael et umot
haolam,
if who won the battle? If the Jews won the battle, so
then you only have 2,000 אמות. amot. We don't have to let
you get home because, you know, presumably you're in a strong position,
especially if we let you keep your arms on you. כאן שנצחו
אומות העולם את עצמן. kan shenitzchu umot haolam et atzman. And the
other case is when the non-Jews won. Now again, this is euphemistic,
so it says when the non-Jews beat themselves, okay, because it doesn't
want to sort of explicitly say the other. But when the non-Jews
won, then you obviously can keep by, you know, you can go
home. You got to, you got to run back so that you
can be safe and secure and then obviously there is no limit.
Okay, so do you have, you had a question Paula?
Yeah, I'm wondering about, you know, it said in this particular case
they, they made this decree that you can do this. Right. And
it apparently stayed in force forever. Right. So apparently the Rabbis based
on one
situation can issue a decree that would go on forever.
Right, because it's, well, first of all, there's two types of decree.
One is just made a תקנה, takanah, like, no, one is like
made a תקנה, takanah, which is, you know, they can say like
the issue about not wearing the shoes. on שבת Shabbos. because of
one case that was a crazy case, whatever, we don't let people
wear these like shoes with nails on שבת. Shabbos Yes, and it's
a רבנן Rabbanan restriction and hopefully it's not too restrictive, but yeah,
sometimes they can do things. Usually they do things because of a
more pervasive concern, but they can make a תקנה takana and that's
what it is. This is a bigger חידוש chidush because here they're
actually allowing חילול שבת, chilul Shabbos, but it comes
through the word תקנה takana maybe is a little bit funny in
this case because it really comes through like a פסק, psak, like
basically saying we are looking at the situation and
assessing that keeping your weapons on you is a פיקוח נפש pikuach
nefesh consideration.
So sure, that's what they can do and there's like a lot
of parameters where they basically say like for example when the רבנן
Rabbanan. say any type of an injury that's from the gums inward
in the mouth is
potentially פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, and they like just set certain parameters.
So that's what's going on here, yeah.
Can we trace when the הלכה halacha became solidified? I mean like
you mention like the ראשונים, Rishonim, yeah.
When you mean the earliest sense of when תחומין were established? Yeah,
I don't know, I mean there the גמרא Gemara did originally attribute
it to שלמה, Shlomo, which I can't remember if it attributed to
שלמה Shlomo עירוב חצירות eruv chatzeiros or or even עירוב תחומין. eruv
techumim. Don't you remember? You had that, we had that גמרא, Gemara
right?
בני אם חכם לבך.
Beni im chacham libcha.
It certainly was עירוב חצירות, eruv chatzeiros, I don't remember if it
was also
עירוב תחומין, eruv techumim, but that's the גמרא Gemara, is just trying
to sort of place it historically. There is no hint, well the
hint is אל יצא איש ממקומו, al yetze ish mimkomo, right, then
the idea that there's an idea of not going out, so the
whole idea of עירוב תחומין eruv techumim that you can place something
and extend it or the idea that even many ראשונים Rishonim say
that even the opinion that it's דאורייתא's d'Oraisa twelve מיל, mil, so
the idea that we shorten it to one מיל, mil, two thousand
אמה. amah Some say it's not דאורייתא d'Oraisa so it would all
be רבנן. Right, so clearly it was at the תנא Tannaitic times,
but exactly when this whole thing started, at which stage I don't
know if there's any evidence. Okay, let's see a little bit further,
yeah.
The bonus point was perhaps the case is referred to as a
תקנה takana because
if you broadcast that the
law is such and such, yeah, you're not only broadcasting it internally,
you're broadcasting it to the enemy.
That's a nice point. So it's important to make that whole point
public. That's a very good point. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this,
okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב נכרים שצרו על
עיירות ישראל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav nochrim shetzaru al ayarot Yisrael,
if the non-Jews sort of besiege Jewish cities, אין יוצאים עליהם בכלי
זיינם ואין מחללים עליהם את השבת, ein yotzim aleihem bichlei zaynam ve'ein
mechalelin aleihem es ha'Shabbos, you cannot fight them with weapons and leave
the city with arms on שבת Shabbos, or violate שבת, Shabbos. which
is quite shocking because it seems to be פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh.
So let's see how the גמרא Gemara explains it. תניא נמי הכי,
tanya nami hachi, we
taught similarly, נכרים שצרו nochrim shetzaru etc, במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim
amurim, the ברייתא Braisa there ends and says when is this true,
שבואו על עסקי ממון, sheba'u al iskei mamon, when they are laying
siege because they want, I don't know, like a
money, meaning like you could imagine that the city did not pay
its not taxes, what's that thing called? Tribute. Meaning the city didn't
pay its tribute, okay, so then you're not allowed to be מחלל
שבת, mechalel Shabbos, pay the money. אבל באו על עסקי נפשות, aval
ba'u al iskei nefashot, but if they're coming because actually to for
life, meaning either that they're really fighting a war, maybe they, I
don't know, you sometimes have examples where they're demanding to hand someone
over, they want to kill him, okay, and so people's lives are
at stake, then יוצאים עליהם בכלי זיין ומחללים עליהם את השבת, yotzim
aleihem bichlei zayan umimechalelin aleihem es ha'Shabbos, then you can fight and
violate שבת. Shabbos Now talking about chronologically, I should say, I mean,
or historically I should say that the earliest I think ever documented
evidence of like sort of like a תורה שבעל פה Torah Sheba'al
Peh moment of innovating a new law, the earliest documented case about
that is in the ספר חשמונאים, Sefer Chashmonaim, right, where they basically
they refused to fight on שבת Shabbos and they got wiped out,
and then they said you know what I think God wants us
to fight on שבת Shabbos, and they did. So that sort of
insight that פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh is דוחה שבת doche Shabbos and
when you're fighting the enemy you can actually fight back on שבת,
Shabbat, that seems to be the first documented example of like תורה
שבעל פה. Torah Sheba'al Peh. Okay anyway, so that's exactly this. Okay,
now ובעיר הסמוכה לספר, uve'ir hasmucha lesefar, if it's a city that
is on the border, אפילו לא באו על עסקי נפשות, afilu lo
ba'u al iskei nefashot, even if they did not come for purpose
for a life and no lives are at risk, אלא על עסקי
תבן וקש, ella al iskei teven vekash, even if it's just an
issue about like straw and stubble, יוצאים עליהם בכלי זיין ומחללים עליהם
את השבת. yotzim aleihem bichlei zayan umimechalelin aleihem es ha'Shabbos. The idea
that the city is besieged if it's a border city is itself
seen as a פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, even if the reason they're
besieging it is not because they're looking to kill anyone. אמר רב
יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Yosef bar Minyomi amar
Rav Nachman, ובבבל, uveBavel, in Babylonia, כעיר הסמוכה לספר דמיא, ke'ir hasmucha
lesefar damya,
it's like a city near a border, which seems bizarre. First of
all the whole idea that you have Jewish cities in בבל Bavel
and so on, and תנא דבי... Tana devei... imagine what the sort
of circumstances were in the time in the משנה mishna: in the
time of in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. And then number two, the
whole Babylonia is סמוכה לספר? smucha lasfar?
So the גמרא Gemara. explains it, ותרגומה, u'targuma, we explained what that
means is נהרדעא, Nehardea, that the city of נהרדעא Nehardea is considered
to be a border city. So at least in theory, if that
was a Jewish city that was being attacked, then you would be
allowed to defend it even on שבת, Shabbat, even if it was
not about a life being at risk.
I notice the Koren has a note that it was on the
border of the Persian Empire for many years and was actually overrun
by the Romans a couple of times. Ah, so it was, and
that is actually true. The Romans did conquer all בבל Bavel a
couple of times.
Right. Right. Oh, so, okay, so that, so then it exactly is
giving that as an example between a border city between Rome and
Persia. Very good. So that would sort of be given like as
an illustration so people can appreciate the importance of border cities.
There's an interesting judgment call between the Persians and the Romans. Right.
That the Romans are always the enemy?
Well, in that time. It's one thing to say that in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael when you're defending a Jewish country and so on,
but to say that so you have a Jewish population in a
foreign country, you care that, rather you'd rather have the Persians in
charge than the Romans in charge.
Well, that was true that even in the time of the גמרא,
Gemara life was much better under the Persians than under the Romans.
You're right, it's an interesting question. Is the גמרא Gemara just using
it as an illustration? Like for example, if we were the Persians
and נהרדעא Nehardea was being attacked, or is the גמרא Gemara actually
saying practically, no, if you find yourself in נהרדעא Nehardea and the
Persians are fighting against the Romans, you can join in. Which actually
is an interesting question because, you know, Jews did serve in foreign
armies. Sometimes they were conscripted, but sometimes actually they actually, you know,
like the I think the לחם משנה, Lechem Mishneh, the classic commentator
on the רמב"ם, Rambam, I think was an officer in, yeah. So
there's like sometimes Jews actually, you know, make career choices of fighting
for foreign armies, and how does that play out? Of course you
can say on שבת, Shabbat, of course once you're in the army,
there are פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh situations. But you're right, it's an
interesting question if you happen to be a citizen in נהרדעא Nehardea
when it was being attacked, would you sort of see yourself as
a bystander or as somebody that would be able to fight to
protect the Persian Empire? Excellent point. You know, I was imagining it
more as a hypothetical situation. All right, let's take a look now
at the next גמרא. Gemara דרש Darsh רב דוסתאי Rav Dostai דמן
בירי, d'min Biri, so רב דוסתאי Rav Dostai from בירי Biri made
the following exposition, the דרשה drasha on the פסוק. pasuk. מאי דכתיב,
Mai d'chtiv, what's meant by the פסוק? pasuk? ויגידו לדוד לאמר, Vayagidu
l'David lemor, they told to דוד David saying, right? So
where's this? I'm just looking here at the exact reference, שמואל א'
כ"ג. Shmuel Aleph Chaf Gimmel. Okay, so they told to דוד David
saying, הנה פלשתים נלחמים בקעילה, Hinei Plishtim nilchamim b'Keilah,
the Philistines are fighting in קעילה, Keilah, והמה
שוסים את הגרנות, v'heima shosim et hagranot, and they are like sort
of attacking the granaries. תנו, Tanu, we taught in a ברייתא, braita,
קעילה עיר הסמוכה לספר היתה. Keilah ir hasmucha lasfar hayta.
This was a city that was on the border,
and they came to help, between, you know, sort of the Jewish
territory and the Philistine territory. והם לא באו אלא
על עסקי תבן וקש, v'hem lo ba'u ela al iskei teven v'kash,
and they were only fighting, it was an issue about like, you
know, it was maybe like a border dispute, it was a question
about straw and stubble. It was not that they were trying to
kill. They were fighting a war, but ultimately the issues were monetary
issues. דכתיב, D'chtiv, והמה שוסים את הגרנות, v'heima shosim et hagranot, that
they were basically biting or sniping at, attacking the granaries. דכתיב, D'chtiv,
so that was exactly the case about a border city, that it
was a monetary dispute. וישאל דוד בה' לאמר, Vayishal David b'Hashem lemor,
and דוד David asked השם Hashem saying, האלך והכיתי בפלשתים האלה? Ha'elech
v'hikiti ba'Plishtim ha'eleh?
Should I go and fight these Philistines? ויאמר ה' אל דוד לך
והכית בפלשתים והושעת את קעילה, Vayomer Hashem el David lech v'hikita ba'Plishtim
v'hoshat et Keilah, and smite the Philistines and you will save קעילה.
Keilah. מאי קא מיבעיא ליה? Mai ka mibaya lei?
So now presumably the issue was to illustrate that this assume it
was on שבת, Shabbat, and you see you're allowed to fight to
protect a border city on שבת, Shabbat even if it's just about
an issue of straw and stubble. But now the גמרא Gemara sort
of steps back from that and says, maybe not. It says מאי
קא מיבעיא ליה, mai ka mibaya lei, what was דוד David asking
God, which would mean he was asking the אורים ותומים Urim v'Tumim
of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. אילימא אי שרי אי אסור, Elima
i sharei i assur, is it forbidden or permitted because it was
a שבת Shabbat, issue? הרי בית דינו של שמואל הרמתי קיים. Harei
beit dino shel Shmuel ha'Ramati kayam.
What are they doing asking God? They should go to a בית
דין, beit din, they should go to שמואל, Shmuel, you go to
a רב. וכי משאלין באורים ותומים על הלכה? V'chi m'shaalin b'Urim v'Tumim
al halacha? Quite, just because the גמרא Gemara is like the other
day we had about משיח Mashiach and אליהו Eliyahu coming on שבת,
Shabbat. whether they go to חוץ לתחום. chutz latchum Why you ask
God a halachic שאלה? sheila? אלא אי מצלח אי לא מצלח, Ela
i mazlach i lo mazlach, he wanted to know would he be
successful or not. דייקא נמי דכתיב, Dayka nami d'chtiv, והכית בפלשתים והושעת
את קעילה, v'hikita ba'Plishtim v'hoshat et Keilah, you will save the city.
שמע מינה, Shma mina, you see that he was asking whether he
would be successful or not. Of course once you say that, it
doesn't prove the issue about defending a border city on שבת. Shabbos?
Okay, anyway. Next משנה. Mishnah. מי שישן בדרך. Mi she'yashan baderech. So
that was going out because you were forced or going out because
of a מצוה. mitzvah Forced you have four אמות, amot, מצוה you
have two thousand אמות. amot מי
שישן בדרך, Mi she'yashan baderech, you were travelling and it was getting
late Friday and you encamped wherever you happened to be. ועמד וראה,
V'amad v'ra'ah, and you got up and you saw... Later after it
was already שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, presumably like the next morning. הרי הוא
סמוך לעיר *Harei hu samuch l'ir*, you say, "Oh my gosh, look,
I was right outside the city. I didn't
realize. City was within two thousand אמות amot, *amot* from where I
camped out here Friday night." הואיל ולא היתה כוונתו לכך *Ho'il v'lo
haita kavanato l'kach*, since when שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat* began, you were not
intending to start in the city, or some say not even not
intending to start, not intending to go to the city, you weren't
aware that there was a city, you cannot say that you were
part of this city. לא יכנס *Lo yikanes*, you can't go into
the city. It doesn't mean you can't go in, it means you're
not like the city, right? Meaning, even if you're within the two
thousand אמות amot *amot*. So again, here is your, this is two
thousand אמות amot, *amot* in every direction, you're here in the middle,
the city's like right over here. So if you're considered to start
in the city, then you get the entire city and two thousand
אמות amot, *amot* outside of it. But nope, you're considered to start
here, not start in the city, so you get to go into
the city up to the two thousand אמות amot *amot* line, but
no further. That's the first opinion. You do not get to be
considered like you started in the city.
Well, you can go, but you can't go fully into the city.
You can only go into the city only up to your two
thousand אמות amot *amot*.
So if you're nineteen
or one thousand nine hundred and ninety-nine אמות amot *amot*, then you
can go one
אמה amah *amah* into the city. Right, exactly.
Well, the גמרא *Gemara* says if you don't know, you basically take
an average step and you assume an average step is an אמה
amah, *amah*, an average stride.
Have a laser beam, right?
Anyway, you can't use on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat*. Anyway, so דברי רבי
מאיר
*Divrei Rabbi Meir*,
that's what רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
אומר יכנס *Rabbi Yehuda omer yikanes*, you can go in. It's like
you started in the city. אמר רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda מעשה היה
ונכנס רבי טרפון בלא מתכוין *Amar Rabbi Yehuda ma'aseh hayah v'nichnas Rabbi
Tarfon b'lo mitkavein*, and once it happened that רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon*
went into a city without intending, meaning he didn't realize that he
was encamped outside the city. He found out when he woke up
and it was like he started in the city. Now, I should
say that what this is basically a קולא *kula*, meaning everybody agrees
that if you started out, if you knew you were in two
thousand אמות amot *amot*, you could be considered like one of the
people of the city. Now that in itself is a bit of
a חידוש chiddush *chiddush* because if I'm here, I can't say I'm
starting my שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* nineteen hundred אמות amot *amot* away from
where I'm currently standing. It's where you're standing or where you put
your עירוב *eiruv*, right? You can't just designate a space even within
your two thousand אמות amot *amot*. So here, even if you know
the city is there, there's a leniency here that we want to
make life easy on you and we allow it to be that
if you're within
two thousand אמות amot *amot*, you're considered as an inhabitant of that
city. That's a קולא *kula* we wouldn't normally apply, that we'd let
you start designating your space not somewhere where you are not physically
present. But that leniency is only when, according to the משנה Mishnah
*Mishnah*, you intended to be in that city, or at least you
were, according to some ראשונים *Rishonim*, aware that that city was there
and intending to go to that city. That would allow you to
be considered to be an inhabitant of the city. Or that's the
debate, if you're completely unaware, that's what's being debated in the משנה
*Mishnah*. Yes?
I'm sorry, I may have forgotten this distinction, but when do we
say that once you're in a city you have access to the
entire city as if it were just one point and when...
When you start שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat* in the city.
When you start שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* in the city, then the whole
city counts as like no space and you have two thousand אמות
amot *amot* outside it. Right. And this leniency is saying if you
were outside the city but within two thousand אמות amot *amot*, we'll
consider it like you started שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* in the city provided
you knew about the city and were intending to go there. But
if you were oblivious, then we're going to debate whether it's considered
like you started in the city or not.
And you're within right in the middle of a city. What? And
it still may end even in the middle of a city.
Right, if it's not like you started in the city, then your
תחום techum, *tchum* could end three feet into the city. Okay. So
the משנה *Mishnah* says, תני ותניא בברייתא *Tani v'tanya b'vraita*, אמר רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda מעשה ברבי טרפון שהיה מהלך בדרך וחשכה לו *Amar
Rabbi Yehuda ma'aseh b'Rabbi Tarfon shehayah mahalech baderech v'chashchah lo*, רבי טרפון
*Rabbi Tarfon* was once going on the way and it got dark
Friday, ולן חוץ לעיר *V'lan chutz l'ir*, and he slept right outside
the city. לשחרית מצאוהו רועי בקר *L'shacharit metzauhu ro'ei vakar*, and he
wasn't aware that he was outside the city. In the morning,
some cowherds found him. אמרו לו *Amru lo*, רבי *Rabbi*, הרי העיר
לפניך *Harei ha'ir l'fanecha*,
look, you're right outside the city. יכנס *Yikanes*, go into the city.
נכנס וישב בבית המדרש *Nichnas v'yashav b'veit hamedrash*. So he got up,
went into the בית מדרש *beit medrash*. What do you do on
שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat*? You go into the study hall. ודרש כל היום
כולו *V'darash kol hayom kulo*, and he taught the entire day. So
you see that even if you're unaware, you can be considered as
part of the city. So אמרו לו *Amru lo*, whatever they said
back to him or those that disagreed, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* said
back, "משם ראיה *Misham re'ayah*, you want to bring a proof from
that? שמא בלבו היתה *Shema b'libo haitah*. How do you know whether
he knew he was within the city
limits? Just 'cause the cowherds told him, it didn't mean he himself
was unaware." או *O*, or here's a better explanation. בית המדרש מובלע
בתוך תחומיו היה *Beit hamedrash muvla b'toch tchumav hayah*. Maybe the בית
מדרש *beit medrash* was within his two thousand אמות amot, *amot*, doesn't
prove he has the whole city. Okay, so that's what's being debated.
Now, מי שישב בדרך ולא ידע שחשכה *Mi sheyashav baderech v'lo yada
shechashchah*,
somebody slept on the way and he didn't realize it was getting
dark, meaning forget being part of the city. That's one special case.
Are we going to consider you if you weren't aware? But you
basically put your head down Friday afternoon and you slept straight through
when שבת Shabbos began. Okay, is this considered like that's where you
were קונה koneh your מקום makom on שבת? Shabbos On the one
hand you could say, "My God, you were physically there and sleeping
there, of course it would be." But there's actually a debate in
the משנה that you might have to be, like, aware when שבת
Shabbos. is beginning that this is where you are starting your שבת.
And if you were unaware and you were sleeping, you know, you're
unconscious, you weren't even aware where you were. Okay, you're unconscious, maybe
you do not, it doesn't that's not defined as establishing your place
for your תחום. techum So, יש לו אלפיים אמה לכל רוח, דברי
רבי יוחנן בן נורי. yeish lo alpayim amah lechol ruach, divrei Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri. רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says
that's where you started your שבת. You have 2,000 אמות amot even
if you were unconscious when שבת began. וחכמים אומרים: אין לו אלא
ארבע אמות. vachachamim omrim: ein lo ela arba amot. The חכמים say
you only have four אמות, amot presumably you are outside, you know,
your original תחום tchum, where you would sort of normally start שבת.
We'll see about that in a minute. Okay. אין לו אלא ארבע
אמות. ein lo ela arba amot. רבי אליעזר אומר: והוא באמצען. Rabbi
Eliezer omer: vehu be'emtza'an. Now this is the question about how do
you measure the four אמות which we saw before, that רבי אליעזר
says you're in the middle so there's really two אמות in each
direction. That's a point that could have been said anytime we say
you only have four אמות. רבי יהודה אומר: לאיזה רוח שירצה ילך.
Rabbi Yehuda omer: le'eizeh ruach sheyirtzeh yelech. רבי יהודה says, again, this
is a this is a sub-debate, I mean or more general debate
of how do you measure the four אמות. רבי אליעזר says it's
two אמות in each direction, and רבי יהודה says you can pick
four אמות in any one direction. So it's not a square that's
eight by eight, it's still four by four, but you can define
where you begin that four by four, you know, where you are
in that four by four square. ומודה רבי יהודה, umodeh Rabbi Yehuda,
but רבי יהודה agrees, שאם בירר לו, she'im birer lo, once you
said, "I'm going four אמות this way," שאינו יכול לחזור בו, she'eino
yachol lachzor bo, then you cannot go back to your original place
and then pick a different four אמות. Okay, so what's the moment
of picking? Do you actually have to walk or just verbalize? Anyway,
that's a sub-debate about how to measure the four אמות.
Would the same apply to the 2,000 אמות?
No, 2,000 אמות clearly it's in all that we know it's in
all directions. Okay.
But if you go 2,000 אמות in that direction,
you can still come back home and go 2,000 in the other
direction. Yeah, yeah, you have yeah, you're a 2,000 אמות, you are
in the middle of a square 4,000 אמות by 4,000 אמות. That's
not debated. Okay, here it's when you have just four אמות total,
where are you in that square?
Why is it different?
Because the whole idea of four אמות is an idea like your
place is four אמות. A space is a four אמה amah square,
like the minimum size of a
place. So therefore whereas so it's only a square and the only
question is where are you in the square? Whereas by the 2,000
אמות, the idea is city limits are 2,000 אמות outside of the
city in every direction. It's a different concept. There's not a concept
of a 4,000 אמה amah by 4,000 אמה amah square. There's a
concept of a 2,000 אמה, amah. you know, sort of limit of
the city, you know, or of your place. So but here the
square is four by four and the question is where are you?
Now, where are we? היו שנים, מקצת אמותיו של זה בתוך אמותיו
של
זה. hayu shenayim, mikzat amotav shel zeh betoch amotav shel zeh. If
there were two people who are חוץ לתחום, chutz latechum. we're getting
outside the whole issue of sleeping. Two people are חוץ לתחום and
they only have four אמות, but their each of their four אמות
overlap, right? So these are my four אמות, these are your four
אמות, we're both stuck outside of the תחום tchum. and they overlap
here. I'm in the middle here, you're in the middle here, the
two אמות here to you know, the two אמות we're four אמות
away from each other, these two אמות overlap. Okay.
So... where are we? היו שנים, מקצת אמותיו של זה בתוך אמותיו
של זה, מביאים ואוכלים באמצע. hayu shenayim, mikzat amotav shel zeh betoch
amotav shel zeh, mevi'im ve'ochlim be'emtza. They can go ahead and bring,
you know, and bring... what, and have a picnic in the middle.
Right. ובלבד שלא יוציא זה משלו לתוך של חברו. uvelvad shelo yotzi
zeh mishelo letoch shel chaveiro. As long as you don't take from
your space, you know, and bring into your friend's space. So in
this you can share everything, but you cannot go ahead and bring
from here into, you know, the space that is not yours. Now
why not? Well, he can take it. Well, no, why not? So
the simple reason is there's a complicated רש״י, but the simple reason
is that we're going to find out later there's a הלכה halacha
that your vessels, you know, and your clothes and everything you own
are also limited by your תחום. tchum Okay. So assuming that what's
within here is your food and your stuff, okay, if you can't
bring you can't place it there or he can't take it there
because it's taking the food's תחום tchum outside of the food's תחום,
tchum. or whatever it is that's being taken out of the תחום.
Okay, so you can use the shared space, but you cannot bring
stuff into the space that is not shared even without leaving it,
because it's limited by your תחום.
So even though this food can eat in the middle, and if
if I'm this guy, I can take it from here to there.
What? I can't take anything from outside of the shared space and
neither can you. Regardless of whose food?
Anything that's not yours. Right. Okay. היו שלושה. hayu shlosha. Now let's
say there were three people. Okay. So, you know, it's basically, you
know, one, two, and then... Whatever. This third guy here, the guy's
in the middle, right? He's overlapping with the two other guys, but
the two guys at the ends are not overlapping with one another.
Okay, so in that case, היו שלושה והאמצעי מובלע ביניהם, Hayu shlosha
veha-emtzai muvla benehem, the middle one is swallowed between them, he's the
one with overlap, הוא מותר עמהם, hu mutar imahem, he can eat
with each of them, you know, turn one way eat with one,
turn the other eat with the other, והן מותרים עמו, vehen mutarim
imo, they can eat with him, ושנים החיצונים אסורים זה עם זה,
ushnayim hachitzonim asurim ze im ze,
but the two outer ones who don't overlap cannot sort of, you
know, use any shared space together. אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon,
it said Rabbi Shimon, למה הדבר דומה, Lema hadavar domeh, what is
this like? לשלוש חצרות הפתוחות זו לזו, Lishalosh chatzerot hapetuchot zu lazu,
three courtyards which are opening one to another, ופתוחות לרשות הרבים, ufetuchot
lireshut harabbim, and they are open into the רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim.
עירבו שתיים עם האמצעית, Irbu shtayim im ha-emtza’it, so here, the basic
example is
now, here’s your three courtyards, remember this is the part that we
had before, right? Everybody was saying oh I thought we were done
with all of that.
Okay, anyway, here’s your three courtyards, here’s the רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim,
okay, so each of them has an opening into the רשות הרבים
reshut harabbim
and they are open into one another. I'll tell you in a
minute why it's important that they have an opening to רשות הרבים.
reshut harabbim. So in that case, פתוחה לרשות הרבים, petucha lireshut harabbim,
עירבו שתיים עם האמצעית, irbu shtayim im ha-emtza’it,
so
if there were two eruvs made, the theory you can make one
big eruv for all three, but what actually happened was we had
one eruv made like this and one eruv made like this, the
middle guy made an eruv with both sides. Okay, so in that
scenario, היא מותרת עמהן והן מותרות עמה, hi muteret imahen vehen mutarot
ima,
so, you know, the middle one can use the shared space, no,
his, you know, use the shared space with the guy on the
left and the guy on the right or the courtyard, והשנים החיצונים
אסורות זו עם זו, vehashnayim hachitzonim asurot zu im zu, but the
two outer courtyards, you know, I cannot go from here and carry
in your space over here. I can carry in the shared space,
but I can't carry in your space because I did not make
an eruv with you and same in the reverse. The reason it’s
relevant that they’re open to רשות הרבים reshut harabbim is if they
weren’t open, all open to רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, and if basically
this only let’s say only this one was open to רשות הרבים
reshut harabbim and this was the street, then
then since the access to the inner one is only through the
outer one, it forces all of them to make an eruv together,
okay, because then you can't sort of be independent of each each
one because you can only get there through the others. We'll see
more about that later.
What if I want to move food? If I'm all the way
to the left, I want to move food all the way to
the right? You just ask you in the middle to to bring
it.
Well, no,
you could do it with both of us, I can do it
with them, but you know, but I’m not doing it with them,
I’m doing it through you.
So there it’s not a תחום issue of taking the food חוץ
לתחום.
In terms of a carrying
issue, it could even be like a Shabbos goy so to speak,
right?
No, well, no.
I guess if it’s... I’m just trying to think if it’s... stopped
in...
I’ll get back to them. Okay, let’s take a look at the
Gemara. בעא רבא, Ba’ei Rava, so Rava asked, מאי קסבר רבי יוחנן
בן נורי? mai kasavar Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri? What does Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri hold, who holds
that even when you were unconscious, that’s where you started your Shabbos?
מאי קסבר רבי יוחנן בן נורי? mai kasavar Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri?
מיסבר קסבר, misbar kasavar, does he hold חפצי הפקר קונים שביתה, cheftzei
hefker konim shevita, that even if something, you saw this before, was
ownerless, meaning then, you know, it doesn't require any sort of any
consciousness in order to say that wherever something is that’s where it
begins Shabbat. So even if something is ownerless and I just mentioned
to you that even even, you know, inanimate objects have a תחום,
they normally go by their owner, but if they’re ownerless their תחום
is where they begin, so even if something is ownerless, קונים שביתה,
konim shevita, then that be that defines where it begins Shabbos is
where it is. So therefore, meaning there's need no no conscious awareness
to for something to be defined where it is, you know, it's
its its place is when Shabbos begins.
ובדין הוא דליפלגי בכלים, uvedin hu deliflu bekelim, and he really could
have said his position by vessels, that even if it's an, you
know, inanimate object begins Shabbos where it starts, certainly a sleeping person.
והא דקמיפלגי באדם, veha dekamipligi be-adam, so why were they debating a
sleeping person? להודיעך כוחן דרבנן, lehodia'acha kochan derabbanan, to tell you the
chiddush of the Rabbis, דאף על גב דאיכא למימר הוא ונעור קנה
ישן נמי קנה, de-af al gav de-ika lemeimar hu vene'or kana yashen
nami kana, because there’s a there’s more of a reason to say
that a sleeping person should work better than an inanimate object because
you could say had he been awake this clearly would have been
where he started, so even asleep it's where he started. קא משמע
לן דלא, ka mashma lan dela, and therefore they’re telling you that
the Rabbis go so far to say that even a sleeping person
does not work. But the one who says it does work would
go so far to say it even works by an inanimate object.
I should point out that in the inanimate object case it’s a
חומרא chumra because if you say the inanimate object is קונה שביתה,
koneh shevita, you’re limited how far you can bring it. If you
don’t say it’s קונה שביתה, koneh shevita, then maybe it acquires it’s
sort of where it starts Shabbat. But if you say an inanimate
object does not sort of establish itself, then it's only would be
defined let's say if I picked it up on Shabbat it would
be defined by me, which is how I want it defined because
then I can take it wherever I can go. Okay, but here,
presumably you—it's the flip—you want to begin שבת presumably where you fell
asleep, and that's where רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri
is saying that it works, that it works. That's one way of
understanding it, that he would even say the same thing by inanimate
object. או דילמא O dilma or perhaps,
קסבר רבי יוחנן בן נורי בעלמא חפצי הפקר אין קונין שביתה. Kasavar
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri be'alma heftzei hefker ein konin shevithah. If it
was really inanimate, then it would not define its—where it starts שבת
where it happened to physically be. הכא היינו טעמא Hacha hainu ta'ama
so we—you need intention. So why does it work here if you're
asleep? הואיל וניעור קני Ho'il venior kanei because had if you had
been awake you would have, ישן נמי קני yashen nami kanei even
if you are asleep. Okay, so yes it requires at least potential
intention, and a sleeping person is different than an inanimate object. So
we don't know what the reason of רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri is. Is it the special case of a person,
or would he even say it by an inanimate object? So אמר
רב יוסף תא שמע Amar Rav Yosef ta shema I'm going to
try to prove to you that רב יוסף Rav Yosef says that—that
רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri would say it even
by an inanimate object. גשמים שירדו מערב יום טוב Geshamim sheyardu me'erev
Yom Tov it rained. Now if it rained right before יום טוב,
Yom Tov, same would be יום טוב Yom Tov or שבת, this
was just the case was יום טוב, Yom Tov, יש להם אלפיים
אמה לכל רוח. Yesh lahem alpayim amah lechol ruach. They are two
thousand אמה from wherever the rain fell. You want to collect the
rain or whatever, so it's defined by where it fell.
Okay, since the rain—means assuming it's not like flowing, otherwise you can't
tell which is—Right.
ביום טוב Be'Yom Tov now if that was if it was ערב
יום טוב. erev Yom Tov. ביום טוב Be'Yom Tov it fell on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, so it didn't start שבת—it didn't start יום
טוב Yom Tov anywhere, it's not defined by a תחום, הרי הן
כרגלי כל אדם. Harei hen keraglei kol adam. It goes by anybody,
which means, there's a question exactly about the means, but for our
purposes we'll say it means whoever picks it up and takes it.
So if it fell on ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov it's
defined its two thousand אמה where it fell. If it fell on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, so obviously you define תחומין when יום טוב
Yom Tov begins and it didn't—it wasn't down here when יום טוב
Yom Tov began. So therefore maybe it's—יש בהם נולד?
Yesh
bahem nolad?
What? We'll talk about—we'll talk about נולד. nolad. So anyway, in that
case since it's not defined when יום טוב Yom Tov begins, it
would be defined by the person who took possession of them on—because—and
because—because all of your objects and this now becomes one of your
objects is defined by your תחום. Okay, so that seems to be
a clear example that an inanimate object, the rain, is defined—if it
was there on ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov is defined by
where it began—where it began יום טוב. Yom Tov. So the גמרא
says like this, אי אמרת בשלמא קסבר רבי יוחנן בן נורי חפצי
הפקר קונין שביתה. Ei amart bishlama kasavar Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri heftzei
hefker konin shevithah. If רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri
holds that even inanimate objects that are ownerless establish their place, so
הא מני רבי יוחנן בן נורי היא. Ha mani Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri hi. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is—so we at least we
now know who the author of this משנה is. The author of
this issue about the rain, it's רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אלא אי
אמרת חפצי הפקר אין קונין שביתה. Ela ei amart heftzei hefker ein
konin shevithah. If רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri doesn't
say ownerless objects, so we don't know of anybody else who might
say it. So הא מני? Ha mani? Who's saying this case by
the rain that the rain goes by where it fell? לא רבי
יוחנן Lo Rabbi Yochanan it's not רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ולא רבנן
velo Rabbanan and not the רבנן. The רבנן don't even allow a
sleeping guy. So clearly what the גמרא is saying is we have
a משנה, a ברייתא braisa rather, that there is some תנא tanna
out there that holds that ownerless objects define שבת where they begin.
And since that is we would like to attribute that to רבי
יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri because we have nobody else
to attribute it to. So יתיב אביי Yativ Abaye so אביי Abaye:
was sitting וקאמר לה להא שמעתא veka'amar lah lehah sham'ata and telling
over this discussion. אמר ליה רב ספרא לאביי Amar leih Rav Safra
le'Abaye so רב ספרא Rav Safra said to אביי: Abaye ודלמא בגשמים
הסמוכים לעיר עסקינן דאנשי אותה העיר דעתם עליהו. Vedilma begeshamim hasmuchim le'ir
askinan de'anshei osah ha'ir da'atam aleihu. Maybe, you know, they saw it
was about to rain and therefore it was not that it was
unintentional. The people were actually knowing, 'Oh great, it's going to rain
and then we'll be able to collect the rain on יום טוב,'
Yom Tov, etc. And therefore it's like they consciously put it down
wherever it fell. I see. No, if it's completely הפקר hefker and
you're unaware of it.
No, I should always have in mind that if it's going to
rain, my mind is on it.
No, no, no, but actually it was—that implicitly it was. Okay, so
therefore you cannot say that it is completely like הפקר hefker in
the sense that, you know, where there was no intentionality. So אמר
ליה amar lei, he said back to him, לא סלקא דעתך. Lo
salka daitach. That doesn't make sense. והתניא Vehatanya and we learned in
the משנה: בור של יחיד כרגלי היחיד. Bor shel yachid keraglei hayachid.
If—if you have a private owned well, then it goes by the
owner. ושל אותה העיר, Veshel osah ha'ir, if it's owned by the
city, כרגלי אותה העיר. keraglei osah ha'ir. Then it—then even if individuals
in the city made their own private עירובי תחומין, eiruvi tchumin, it
goes by the whole city, means two thousand אמה around the city.
Even though, you know, you are—you made a תחום and you're going
further to the east and you're going further to the west. If
it's owned by the city, it goes by the general תחום of
the city. Okay,
fine, no חידוש yet. ושל עולי בבל, Veshel olei Bavel, if it
is for the people that are coming up from בבל, Bavel, meaning
it's there—it's not owned by a city, it's out in the middle
of the road of the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and the highway
and it's basically הפקר, hefker, anybody can use it who's, you know,
who's taking it. כרגלי הממלא. Keraglei hamemalei. It goes by the person
who fills it up, which means that they are—it's not קונה שביתה.
koneh shevithah. The well
in—the water in this well that is for עולי בבל olei Bavel
for the travelers is ownerless, as opposed to the private or the
one owned by the city, and therefore it says it's not limited
by two thousand אמה. from the well. It goes from the space
of the person that picks it up and takes possession of it.
So that's the idea that חפצי הפקר cheftzei hefker are not קונה
שביתה. koneh shevitah. דתניא, D’tanya, that's one ברייתא, braita, but we have
another ברייתא braita that says בור של שבטים, bor shel Shvatim, if
you have a well owned by the שבטים, Shvatim, meaning by כלל
ישראל, Klal Yisrael, okay, so that's considered to be—it's interesting. You could
have said that that's, you know, owned, it's owned by all of
כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. But again, but all of כלל ישראל Klal
Yisrael doesn't have one תחום. So that is seen as effectively the
same as being ownerless. So you have this well that's owned by
כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, okay, יש
להם אלפיים אמה לכל רוח, yesh lahem alpayim amah le-chol ruach, it
goes two thousand אמות from where—from from the well. So you have
one ברייתא braita that says an ownerless well, it goes by the
guy who picked up the water on שבת. You have another one
that says it goes by where two thousand אמות from the well.
So this is exactly the debate of ownerless objects. Do they have—do
they do they define their place based on where they start at
two thousand אמות in every direction, or do they not define their
space until somebody place—until somebody picks them up? One minute. So how
do you deal with this contradiction? אלא שמע מינה, elah shma mina,
it must be it's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. הא רבי יוחנן
בן נורי הא רבנן. ha Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri ha Rabbanan. That
this is the same debate we have in our משנה. So basically
we know there's evidence out there that there are תנאים Tannaim that
hold that חפצי הפקר cheftzei hefker is קונה שביתה koneh shevitah by
this case of the well or by this case of the rain
and therefore—and we know it's debated. And therefore it makes sense to
map that debate on the debate of our משנה about the guy
who fell asleep. Okay, so אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said
back to him—I think אביי Abaye to רב ספרא, Rav Safra, הכי
קאמר רב ספרא. hachi ka’amar Rav Safra. No, not אביי Abaye, to—who
was talking to who? רב ספרא Rav Safra said to אביי, Abaye
so yes, so אביי Abaye. said back—wait a minute—I'm getting confused who
said to what. Anyway, אלא הכי קאמר רב ספרא elah hachi ka’amar
Rav Safra and הכי... hachi... I'm sorry, wait wait. כי אתא לקמיה
דרב יוסף, ki ata le-kamei de-Rav Yosef, I skipped a line, that's
what. כי אתא לקמיה דרב יוסף, ki ata le-kamei de-Rav Yosef, okay,
so now—so that was what רב ספרא Rav Safra said to אביי.
Abaye So now אביי Abaye, came to רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. אמר
ליה, and he said to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, הכי קאמר רב
ספרא, hachi ka’amar Rav Safra, this is what רב ספרא Rav Safra
said to me. He said, you know, maybe they were planning on
raining and he tried to dismiss the idea of חפצי הפקר. cheftzei
hefker. והכי אהדרי ליה ve-hachi ahadarei lei and I responded to him
that there clearly is a position out there of חפצי הפקר, cheftzei
hefker, this issue of the wells, and therefore I wanted to map
it on the debate of רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri and the רבנן. אמר ליה, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said
to אביי, ומאי לא תימא ליה מגופא? ve-mai lo tima lei mi-gufa?
Why didn't you tell him from the very case of the rain
itself that clearly it's not that they were planning on it raining
and that defined it? Why? אי סלקא דעתך ei salka daatach כשמים
הסמוכים לעיר דינן, k’shammim hasmuchi le-ir dinan,
you wanted to say—you know, רב פפא Rav Papa wanted to say
that the—you can't prove from the rain case because maybe they knew
it was going to rain and therefore it was like they had
intended for, you know, where it fell. If that's true, הא יש
להם אלפיים אמה לכל רוח, ha yesh lahem alpayim amah le-chol ruach,
then why would it say that the rain goes two thousand אמות
from where it fell? הא כרגלי אנשי אותה עיר מיבעיא ליה. ha
k’raglei anshei osa ir mibaya lei. It should be like the people
of the city because then it becomes as if it were owned
by the city. So meaning, again, just to step back, right, the
ברייתא braita says that if the rain falls on ערב יום טוב,
Erev Yom Tov, it is defined by where it fell. So that
wanted to be a proof that חפצי הפקר cheftzei hefker are קונה
שביתה. koneh shevitah. And the answer was, no, no, no, maybe it's
that the people in the city knew it was going to fall
and it's like they put it down there. So the גמרא says
no. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef said back no, because if it's—they're
קונה שביתה koneh shevitah by themselves, that explains why the ברייתא braita
says they're two thousand אמות from where they fell. But if it's
like we the people of the city put it down there, then
it's like it's saying it's owned by we of the people of
the city and it should be defined by our two thousand אמות,
not the two thousand אמות where it fell. So the upshot of
all of this is is that there's Tannaitic evidence that there's a
position out there that חפצי הפקר cheftzei hefker are קונה שביתה. koneh
shevitah. Either the rain goes by where it fell or the well,
the water of the well's two thousand אמות from from where it
began. There's other positions out there that no, it's not קונה שביתה
koneh shevitah and it goes by the person that takes possession of
them. And the גמרא’s saying let's map that debate on the sleeping
person and say the issue of the sleeping person is not just
because he could have woken up, ultimately this is the debate of
do you need consciousness at all when even inanimate objects can they
be קונה שביתה koneh shevitah where they are or not. So we'll
continue this tomorrow.